Princeton Ethiopic Manuscripts, late 1600s-1900s: Finding Aid C0776
Manuscripts Division
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 21: Homily [in Honor] of [the Archangel] Michael (Dərəsanä Mika'el), 1889-1913; 2 cols., 20 lines. Paper Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. Plain wooden boards, broken upper board, stitched and leather covered spine. Fols. 89v, 90r, 139r-140v, 142rv: Blank (deliberately left blank in middle of manuscript for paintings). Fols. 1vr and 141rv were originally the leather cover. Red and black yarns through upper folios mark the monthly readings. (Unitid 21)
  Illustrations: Fols. 2r, 12r, 21r: Häräg.
  Note in Amharic on the lower wooden board: "This wooden board will stay until it is changed."
  Fols. 2r, 9rv, 10r, 11r, 12r, passim: Owner's name Wäldä Mika'el and scribe's name Gäbrä Kiros appear at the beginning of each homily.
  The second owner has partially erased the original owner's name from the manuscript every time it appears and inserted over it "Habtä Wäld."
  Fol. 141r: A note in another hand in Amharic: "This book belongs to [owner's name erased] of Däbrä Səlaləš [famous church in Gojam, Ethiopia]. Please commission someone to create a painting and binding [for this manuscript]. Then you can send it to me when it is convenient. The remaining [to be written] are Gospel of John, Secret of Heaven, Collection of Images, and Book of Penitence and Penance. It will be for the next generation [lit. son]."
  Fol. 141v: Pen trial.
  Loose folio with cataloging information and "bought by John Mason." Gift of John Mason.
  References: For the print Ge'ez version, see Dərəsanä Mika'el Wä-dərsanä Rufa'el Mäləkə'a Mika'el Wä Mäləkə'a Rufa'el, Täsfa Printing press, Addis Ababa 1940 EC, pp. 11–205 For further discussion see Encyclopedia Aethiopica, vol. 2, p. 139-140.
  - Hədar, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 2r-12r. (Unitid 21)
  - Homily by Dämatewos, Bishop of Alexandria, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 2r-10r. (Unitid 21)
  - Miracle, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 10r-11r. (Unitid 21)
  - Synaxary Entry: Mission to Joshua, Son of Nun, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 11rv. (Unitid 21)
  - Miracle, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 10r-11r. (Unitid 21)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 11v-12r. (Unitid 21)
  - Tahəśaś, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 12r-20v. (Unitid 21)
  - Homily, Author Not Given, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 12r-18v. (Unitid 21)
  - Miracle, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 19r-20r. (Unitid 21)
  - Synaxary Entry: Mission of the Archangel to Rescue the Three Holy Children, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 20rv. (Unitid 21)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 20v. (Unitid 21)
  - Tərr, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 21r-35v. (Unitid 21)
  - Homily on the Glory of St Michael the Archangel, Author Not Given, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 21r-33r. (Unitid 21)
  - Miracle, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 33r-35r. (Unitid 21)
  - Synaxary Entry: Mission of the Archangel to Jacob, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 35rv. (Unitid 21)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 35v. (Unitid 21)
  - Yäkkatit, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 35v-42v. (Unitid 21)
  - Homily, Author Not Given, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 35v-40r. (Unitid 21)
  - Miracle, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 40r-42r. (Unitid 21)
  - Synaxary Entry: Mission of the Archangel to Samson the Giant, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 42rv. (Unitid 21)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 42v. (Unitid 21)
  - Mäggabit, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 42v-66v. (Unitid 21)
  - Homily by Abba Yohannəs, Bishop of Antioch, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 42v-63r. (Unitid 21)
  - Miracle, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 63r-66r. (Unitid 21)
  - Synaxary Entry: Mission of the Archangel to Balaam, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 66rv. (Unitid 21)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 66v. (Unitid 21)
  - Miyazya, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 66v-76v. (Unitid 21)
  - Homily of Yohannəs the Orthodox, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 66v-72v. (Unitid 21)
  - Miracle, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 72v-75v. (Unitid 21)
  - Synaxary entries: Mission of the Archangel to the Prophet Jeremiah, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 75v-76v. (Unitid 21)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 76v. (Unitid 21)
  - Gənbot, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 76v-83r. (Unitid 21)
  - Homily by Yohannəs, Bishop of Ethiopia, Who Came After Bishop Yəśhaq, on the Conflict Between the Consort of King Arqadewos and John Chrysostom, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 76v-79r. (Unitid 21)
  - Miracle, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 79r-82v. (Unitid 21)
  - Synaxary entry: Mission of the Archangel to Habakkuk, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 82v-83r. (Unitid 21)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 83r. (Unitid 21)
  - Säne, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 83v-96r. (Unitid 21)
  - Homily on the Family of Astäraniqos and Euphemia, by Yohannəs, Bishop of Aksum, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 83v-91v. (Unitid 21)
  - Miracle, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 91v-94v. (Unitid 21)
  - Synaxary entry: the Building of the Church of the Archangel in Place of a Pagan Temple in Alexandria, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 94v-96r. (Unitid 21)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 96r. (Unitid 21)
  - Hamle, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 96r-105r. (Unitid 21)
  - Homily on the Wicked Wealthy Man Whose Property Was Inherited by the Son of His Poor Neighbor [by Bishop Yohannəs], 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 96r-102r. (Unitid 21)
  - Miracle, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 102r-104r. (Unitid 21)
  - Synaxary entry: Mission to the Camp of Sennacherib, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 104r-105r. (Unitid 21)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 105r. (Unitid 21)
  - Nähase, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 105r-117v. (Unitid 21)
  - Homily on the Book of the Angels that Came from Jerusalem, Author Not Given, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 105r-109r. (Unitid 21)
  - Miracle, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 109v-117r. (Unitid 21)
  - Synaxary entry: Mission of the Archangel to the Emperor Constantine, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 117rv. (Unitid 21)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 117v. (Unitid 21)
  - Mäskäräm, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 117v-122v. (Unitid 21)
  - Homily on Not Worshipping Other Gods, Author Not Given, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 117v-121r. (Unitid 21)
  - Miracle, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 121r-122r. (Unitid 21)
  - Synaxary entry: Mission to Prophet Isaiah, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 122v. (Unitid 21)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 122v. (Unitid 21)
  - Təqəmt, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 123r-132v. (Unitid 21)
  - Homily on the Need to Make the Angels Sureties by Honoring Them, Author Not Given, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 123r-127v. (Unitid 21)
  - Miracle, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 127v-131r. (Unitid 21)
  - Synaxary entry: Mission to Prophet Samuel, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 131r-132r. (Unitid 21)
  - Greeting to the Archangel, Sälam, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 132rv. (Unitid 21)
    Fols. 132v-141r: Asmat [hidden names] in original hand.
  - Prayer for the Current King of Ethiopia, Given as Menilek (r. 1889–1913), 1 item Located on folio 132v. (Unitid 21)
  - Image of Saint Michael, 1889-1913; 1 item Located on folio 133r-138v. (Unitid 21)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 22: Psalter. Dawit, early 20th century; 1 col. [fols. 5r-133v], 25 lines; 2 col. [fols. 34-147], 25 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. Wooden boards, stamped red leather, covered spine. Unusually square and thick manuscript for a Psalter. Red yarns through upper folios and words mark the daily readings: Monday (fol. 1r), Tuesday (fol. 39r), Wednesday (fol. 77r), Thursday (fol. 109r), Friday (fol. 131v), Saturday (fol. 149v), Sunday (fol. 165r). (Unitid 22)
  Owner: Wäldä Qirqos.
  - Psalms, early 20th century; 1 item Located on folio 5r-115v. (Unitid 22)
  - Canticles of the Prophets of the Old and New Testaments, early 20th century; 1 item Located on folio 116r-127r. (Unitid 22)
  - Song of Songs, early 20th century; 1 item Located on folio 127v-133v. (Unitid 22)
  - Praise of Mary (Wəddase Maryam), early 20th century; Located on folio 134r-143r. (Unitid 22)
    - Monday, early 20th century; 1 item Located on folio 134r-135r. (Unitid 22)
    - Tuesday, early 20th century; 1 item Located on folio 135r-136v. (Unitid 22)
    - Wednesday, early 20th century; 1 item Located on folio 136v-138r. (Unitid 22)
    - Thursday, early 20th century; 1 item Located on folio 138r-140r. (Unitid 22)
    - Friday, early 20th century; 1 item Located on folio 140r-141v. (Unitid 22)
    - Saturday, early 20th century; 1 item Located on folio 141v-142r. (Unitid 22)
    - Sunday, early 20th century; 1 item Located on folio 142r-143r. (Unitid 22)
  - Gate of Light, 1900s; 1 item Located on folio 143v-147v. (Unitid 22)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 23: Images (Mäləkə'a), Miracle of Mary (Tä'ammərä Maryam), Miracle of Jesus (Tä'ammərä Iyassus), Prayer to Jesus and Mary, Mystagogia (Təməhrətä Həbu'a), and Other Prayers, late 19th century; 1 col., 16 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Two miniatures. Partial, open leather case without slip or strap. Wooden boards, both broken and sewn. Stitched and open spine (Unitid 23)
  Illustration: Fol. 12r: Häräg.
  Illustration: Fol. 111v: Miniature added later of the Virgin Mary with the Christ Child and the angels.
  Illustration: Fol. 112r: Drawing added later in pencil and blue and red ink of the owner, holding a cross and prayer beads, looking at the miniature on the opposite page of the Virgin Mary. With a caption stating "Wäldä Qirqos appeals to you [the Virgin Mary]."
  Fol. 1rv: Pencil scrawls.
  Fol. 19r: The owner or benefactor's name is given as Kənfä Mika'el.
  Fol. 111r: In different, later hand, it says "This book belongs to Abba Fəsəha Wäldä Täklä Hayəmanot."
  Fol. 112v: Partial Ge'ez alpabet.
  References: See references listed in manuscript no. 7, 8, and 11.
  - Collection of Devotional Readings, late 19th century; Located on folio 2r-112v. (Unitid 23)
    - Vision of John, Son of Thunder, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 2r-11v. (Unitid 23)
    - The Angels' Praise of Mary (Yəweddəsəwa Mäla'əkət), late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 12r-14v. (Unitid 23)
    - Vision of John, Son of Thunder, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 2r-11v. (Unitid 23)
    - Image of Icon of the Virgin Mary, Mäləkə'a Sə'əl, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 14v-18v. (Unitid 23)
    - Introductory Rite from Mu'alləqa, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 18v-23v. (Unitid 23)
    - On the Five Lamentations of Mary, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 23v-24v. (Unitid 23)
    - First Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 24v-28v. (Unitid 23)
      How the Virgin Mary saved the soul of the cannibal of Qəmər (Budge, Mary, 29; Strelcyn 32.16.29).
    - Second Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 24v-28v. (Unitid 23)
    - Third Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 29v-31r. (Unitid 23)
      How the Virgin Mary carried a sick person from the Monastery of the Pilgrims to Jerusalem and showed him where Jesus was crucified and buried and baptized him in the waters of the Jordan (Budge, Mary, 9; Strelcyn 32.16.9).
    - Fourth Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 31r-34v. (Unitid 23)
      How the Virgin Mary appeared to a Roman youth called Zacharias who crowned her icon with roses and how she saved him from bandits because they saw roses flowing from his mouth when he recited her Hail Mary and how they converted and became monks (Budge, Mary, 10).
    - Fifth Miracle of Mary, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 34v-35v. (Unitid 23)
      How the Virgin Mary helped a wealthy woman from Caesarea during a painful childbirth (not in Budge).
    - First Miracle of Jesus, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 36r-37v. (Unitid 23)
      How the midwife Salome glorified Jesus (Strelcyn 16, 3).
    - Second Miracle of Jesus, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 38r-40r. (Unitid 23)
      How Jesus saved the adulterer from stoning (Strelcyn 16, 14?).
    - Third Miracle of Jesus, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 40r-42r. (Unitid 23)
    - Prayer to Jesus and the Virgin Mary, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 42v-56r. (Unitid 23)
      Text edited in S. Grebaut, see Strelcyn, p. 29.
    - Hours of the Night, Nə'i Habey (Excerpt), late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 56r-58r. (Unitid 23)
    - Mystagogia, Təməhrətä Həbu'a (Strelcyn 9.2), late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 58v-65r. (Unitid 23)
    - Synaxarium Entry for Säbsətəyanos Martyrdom, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 65rv. (Unitid 23)
    - Image of Mary, Mälkə'a Maryam, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 66r-78v. (Unitid 23)
    - Image of Jesus, Mälkə'a Iyässus, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 78v-90v. (Unitid 23)
    - Greeting to Saint George, Bähäkä Giyorgis, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 91r-94r. (Unitid 23)
    - Image of Michael, Mälkə'a Mika'el, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 94r-105r. (Unitid 23)
    - Image of Gabriel, Mälkə'a Gabri'el, late 19th century; 1 item Located on folio 105r-111r. (Unitid 23)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 24: Book of Missal (Mäshafä Qəddase), 1939-1945; 2 cols., 17-19 lines (varies from quire to quire). Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Two miniatures. No case. Wooden boards, stitched and open spine. Fol. 1r: Blank. (Unitid 24)
  Illustration: Fol. 41v: Häräg.
  Fol. 1v. Pen trial, scrawls.
  Illustration: Fols. 2rv: Seal of the Anaphora (host bread) ink and pencil drawing, with illegible text in pencil and some scrawls.
  Fols. 19rv, 23v, 29r: Bishop Yohannəs [1939-1945 EC] is mentioned.
  Fol. 37v: Bishop Qerəlos [1926-1950 EC] is mentioned.
  Fols. 20v, 37r: King Iyassu [1913-1916 EC] is mentioned.
  Fol. 50v: King Mənilək [1889-1913 EC] is mentioned.
  Fols. 40v, 41v, 42r, 58v-62v: With musical notation.
  References: Daoud-Mersie, Liturgy. For a detailed discussion, see Ernst Hammerschmidt, Studies in the Ethiopic Anaphoras, second revised edition, (Stuttgart 1987); Encyclopedia Aethiopica, vol. 1, p. 251-253.
  - Missal, 1939-1945; Located on folio 3r-62v. (Unitid 24)
    - Order of the Egyptian Fathers, 1939-1945; 1 item Located on folio 3r-9v. (Unitid 24)
    - Ordinary of the Mass, 1939-1945; 1 item Located on folio 9v-41v. (Unitid 24)
    - Anaphora of the Apostles, 1939-1945; 1 item Located on folio 41v-58v. (Unitid 24)
    - Anaphora of Our Lord (With Musical Notation), 1939-1945; 1 item Located on folio 58v-62v. (Unitid 24)
      Starts in the original hand and then switches on 59r to a different hand. It is incomplete at the end (the prayer called "Pilot of the Soul" is not written).
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 25: Psalter. Dawit, 1700s; 1 col. [fols. 3r-96r], 24 lines; 2 col. [fols. 96r-105v], 26 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. Wooden boards covered in stamped red leather, covered spine. (Unitid 25)
  Illustrations: Fols. 3r, 13v, 19r, 26r, 35v, 48r, 53v, 65v, 73r, 83r, 96r: Häräg.
  Fols. 1rv, 2v, 106rv, 107v: Pencil scrawls and pen trial.
  Fols. 2r, 107r: Pencil notes, in a later hand, on family birthdays, including some in 1935, 1937, 1940 EC.
  Fol. 105v: Scribe's name Haylä Maryam appears in the original text. He has written a note at the end of the manuscript that states: "Bless God who helped me, a sinner and his servant, Haylä Maryam, who is also called Bahərä Təbäb, and the one who commissioned [owner's name erased] [this manuscript] to finish in health and peace."
  Owner's name erased.
  Scribe: Haylä Maryam.
  - Psalms, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 3r-83r. (Unitid 25)
  - Canticles of the Prophets of the Old and New Testaments, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 83r-91r. (Unitid 25)
  - Song of Songs, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 91r-96r. (Unitid 25)
  - Praise of Mary (Wəddase Maryam), 1700s; Located on folio 96r-103r. (Unitid 25)
    - Sunday, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 96r-97r. (Unitid 25)
    - Monday, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 97rv. (Unitid 25)
    - Tuesday, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 97v-98v. (Unitid 25)
    - Wednesday, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 98v-99v. (Unitid 25)
    - Thursday, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 99v-101r. (Unitid 25)
    - Friday, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 101r-102r. (Unitid 25)
    - Saturday, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 102r-103r. (Unitid 25)
  - Gate of Light, 1700s; 1 item Located on folio 103r-105v. (Unitid 25)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 26: Antiphonary for the Year (Dəggwa), 1800s; 2 cols., 20 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. No case. Glossy wooden boards, stitched and open spine. Fols. 1v, 2v, 92rv, 97r: Blank (Unitid 26)
  Fol. 94v: Errata, a paragraph that was omitted earlier in the manuscript is included here.
  Fols. 1r, 2r, 97v: Pen trial and pencil scrawls.
  In small hand throughout, with musical notations.
  References: Aməstu Säwatəwä Zemawoč, Bərhanənna Sälam Press, Addis Ababa 1965 EC; Encyclopedia Aethiopica, vol. 2, p. 123-124.
  - Excerpt from Dəggwa, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 1r. (Unitid 26)
  - Antiphonary for the Year, 1800s; Located on folio 3-96v. (Unitid 26)
    - Antiphonary for the Year (Dəggwa), 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 3r-94r. (Unitid 26)
    - Variation of Hallelujah (Anqäs Haleta), 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 95r-96v. (Unitid 26)
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 27: Psalter. Dawit, 1800s; 1 col. [fols. 5r-131v], 23 lines; 2 col. [fols. 132-145], 23 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Twelve miniatures. Leather case. Glossy wooden boards, stitched and open spine. Rebound with machine-made twine. Fols. 24v, 34v, 45r, 55r, 65r, 75r, 85r, 95r, 105r, 113r, 121r, 131r, 141r: Quires are marked with Ethiopic numerals: quire 1, 2, etc. (Unitid 27)
  Illustrations: Fols. 5r, 11r, 17v, 24r, 32r, 40r, 45v, 53v, 63v, 71r, 76r, 87v, 98v, 101v, 107v, 113v, 125v, 132r: Häräg.
  Nontraditional, unique drawings added later, in the 1900s; captions not in same hand as original manuscript. Pen and ink wash. Not painted over text.
  Illustration: Fol. 1r: Drawing of David: offering to fight Goliath.
  Illustration: Fol. 2r: Drawing of David: encountering Goliath, and another of David: slaying Goliath. David holds his slingshot and Goliath's sword. Caption states in Ge'ez "David who killed the powerful Goliath".
  Illustration: Fols. 2v-3r: Drawing of Ethiopians lion hunting with rifles and other hunting paraphernalia. The lion appears in front of a tree. With the caption: "The hunter with the servants who carry the rifles." Below the lion is a crude imitation of the miniature in pencil.
  Illustration: Fol. 3v: Drawing of Saint George: slaying the dragon, with eyewitness.
  Illustration: Fol. 4v: Drawing of Ethiopians sword-fighting.
  Illustration: Fol. 107v: Drawing of David: slaying Goliath. David holds his slingshot and Goliath's sword. Captions state in Ge'ez: "David who killed the powerful Goliath" and "Goliath died."
  Illustration: Fol. 125r: Drawing of two horizontal spears below text.
  Illustrations: Fol. 146v: Two drawings. First drawing of David: anointed. David in middle, servant on left holding the cup, Samuel on right anointing. Captions from left to right "servant," "David," and "Samuel, prophet of God, anoints David for his kingship." Second drawing of David: as musician. He is playing the harp while a servant looks on from the left.
  Illustration: Fol. 147r: Drawing of Ethiopian church singers with musical instruments. Caption: "These scholars sing for Abba Yohannəs, who finished his [spiritual] combat with patience."
  Illustration: Fol. 147v: Drawing of the Virgin Mary with the Christ Child and Archangels Michael (left) and Gabriel (right). Caption from left to right: " Saint Mika'el," "With Her Beloved Son," and "Saint Gäbrə'el."
  Illustration: Fol. 148r: Drawing of Saint George: slaying the dragon. Caption: "Saint Giyorgis."
  Fols. 1r, 148v: Pen trial and in crude, later hand, a note of ownership: "This Psalter belongs to Wäsäne."
  Fol. 1v: In crude, later hand, a note of ownership: "This Psalter belongs to Wäsäne."
  Fol. 145r: Pen trial in pencil and ink (introductory hymn for Psalter).
  Fol. 146r: Notes of the later transaction of this manuscript. A seller's name is mentioned: Alläqqa Tädlä; a buyer's name is mentioned: Ato Awəgəčäw.
  - Excerpt from the Psalter of the Virgin, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 1r. (Unitid 27)
    In another hand.
  - Excerpts from the Ordinary Prayer of the Mass, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 1v. (Unitid 27)
  - Morning Prayer, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 4r. (Unitid 27)
    In Amharic in another hand in purple ink and pencil.
  - Psalms, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 5r-113r. (Unitid 27)
  - Canticles of the Prophets of the Old and New Testaments, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 113v-125r. (Unitid 27)
  - Song of Songs, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 125v-131v. (Unitid 27)
  - Praise of Mary (Wəddase Maryam), 1800s; Located on folio 132r-141r. (Unitid 27)
    - Monday, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 132rv. (Unitid 27)
    - Tuesday, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 132v-134r. (Unitid 27)
    - Wednesday, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 134r-136r. (Unitid 27)
    - Thursday, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 136r-137v. (Unitid 27)
    - Friday, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 137v-139r. (Unitid 27)
    - Saturday, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 139r-140r. (Unitid 27)
    - Sunday, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 140r-141r. (Unitid 27)
  - Gate of Light, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 141r-145r. (Unitid 27)
  - List of Šäwa Kings, 1800s; 1 item Located on folio 145v-146r. (Unitid 27)
    In crude, later hand.
- Princeton Ethiopic Manuscript No. 28: Psalter. Dawit, 1900s; 1 col. [1r-59r], 24 lines; 2 col. [59r-75v], 24 lines. Parchment Codex. Written in black and red ink. Eleven miniatures. Leather case. Wooden boards, lower stamped red leather board is original to the manuscript, upper board is leather and newer. Stitched and partially open spine. The first half of the Psalter is missing and the first quire has folios out of sequence. The whole has unrelated miniatures painted over text (probably to increase its sales value). Fol. 1r: Text erased (originally was the beginning of Psalm 91) to disguise that the book was divided into half (probably for the market). Fol. 1r, 76rv: Blank. (Unitid 28)
  Illustration: Fol. 2r: Miniature of the Holy Trinity seated with one garment.
  Illustration: Fol. 8v: Miniature of Saint George slaying the Dragon.
  Illustration: Fol. 16v: Miniature of the Virgin Mary with the Christ Child and angels with drawn swords.
  Illustration: Fol. 24v: Miniature of Christ: Crowned with Thorns, and Jews with swords on his left and right.
  Illustration: Fol. 32v: Miniature of the Christ: Crucifixion: One Cross, with the Virgin Mary and John the Evangelist and other women.
  Illustration: Fol. 40v: Miniature of Virgin Mary with her parents Joachim and Hannah (Anna).
  Illustration: Fols. 43r, 59r: Häräg.
  Illustration: Fol. 48r: Miniature of Christ with the Apostle Peter.